let's discuss now some other benefits
of virtualization one interesting thing
is that once you are able to virtualize your
hardware and through an hypervisor run several
guest operating systems and processes within each
guest operating system you can do something you
could not really do before and it is
related to multi-core CPUs or architectures
in which you have actually multiple
CPUs what you can do is that you can
dedicate a specific subset of the cores of one
cpu or maybe a subset of the CPUs to a specific
guest operating system and that has an interesting
implication that is something that did not really
exist before virtualization you might end up in
situations in which the program you're writing and
later executing as a either a set
of processes that are communicating
with inter-process communication at the OS level
or most likely a multi-threaded process can have
a parallelism degree that is actually fitting
the number of physical cores you have in your
virtual machine so in that case you might be able
to do some optimization at the code level that
is very specific to the number of cores you are
going to use because now you know how many cores
you are going to use it's for a specific a virtual
machine that will run on a specific hardware
if you think about large industries like google
where they have a lot of servers and they might
have some specific applications that are running
then they can make versions of these applications
that are really taking advantage of the
let's say optimal level of the resources
of each virtual machine once they associate a
specific number of cores and/or cpus to that
virtual machine the other nice
property of virtualization is that of
deduplication deduplication is something
you usually do for the file system I'm not
describing it now in too much detail but
the basic idea is that you can create a
sort of middleware or a layer in your file system
that before writing each block checks whether that
specific block is already stored maybe it belongs
to a different file but it's already stored on the
disk okay you do this basically using hash
functions so if you keep for each block it's
hash and you have a registry of all the hashes when
you're trying to write a block and you already see
that it's hash is registered because it has
already been written as part of another file
then instead of actually
writing the block you just
keep track of the fact that that specific block
of that specific file is actually found somewhere
else now this kind of  deduplication
now you can do it even at the memory level
it's not really surprising if you
think back at virtual memory and
copy-on-write mechanisms at this point it
should be clear why you really want to decouple
the logical representation of memory from the
physical one the example here is that of a
hypervisor running a set of operating systems if
you think that all these operating systems might
be actually the same operating system it means
that all the text portion of the processes that
belong to these operating systems the
ones of the operating systems not the user process
they will all be the same because it's always
the same operating system so you can play this
deduplication at the memory keeping only one
copy in the physical memory of in this example the
parts that belong to the operating system while
letting believe each operating system that it has
actually its own copy of the memory so it's exactly
what you do with the processes when you do CoW
now you can do for entire operating
systems with deduplication of the memory